Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - The Dear Land from Destruction to Construction, PAL VHS [TRT:0:16:24] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 330, Video-cassette ME202)
    Made by the Public Authority for Agricultural Affairs and Fish Resources.
  - The Terrorist and the Superpower, NTSC VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 330, Video-cassette ME203)
    Producer: Frontline and NY Times
    Original Credits: Reporter: Lowell Bergman. Produced by Martin Smith
    Frontline documentary about Osama Bin Laden and his engagement with the United States. Interviews with many including, Prudence Bushnell, US Ambassador to Kenya during the bombing of American Embassy in Kenya, Ahmed Sattar, who says that the United States is at war with Islam.
    Original starts at 00:51:00.
  - Desert Shield-Tape 9, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:37:00] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME207)
    Producer: Department of Air Force. D0301VTC900536
    Shots of planes taking off from aircraft carriers, shot of a military dentist, soldiers flying in supply helicopters over the desert, Saudi and American administrative personnel at work, planes refueling in air, interviews with medical personnel, war readiness training brief sessions, shots of tanks and other war machinery in the desert, also machinery being loaded onto ships, soldiers building trenches in the desert, interviews with soldiers guarding bases, shots of desert at night with infrared, stopping a vehicle and checking the identification of the soldier, tape cuts.
  - Desert Shield-Tape 10, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:59:18] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME208)
    Producer: Department of the Air Force. Tape ID#D0301-VTC-90-0536
    Tape 10 covers portion of activities and events before Desert Storm. Shows USMC AV-8Bs taking off ship; 56th Tactical Air Command (TAC) Hospital Team performing neck surgery; patriot missile launchers; stinger missile launchers; United States Air Force (USAF) E-3A Air Warning and Control System (AWACS) landing; weather facilities; Sheridan M5 tanks; F-15C; UH-60A; OH-58D; Bae Hunter; KC-10; General H. Norman Schwarzkopf, III; refueling of F-117A from KC-135. Includes speech by General Michael J. Dugan.
    Individual scenes include Series of scenes, in flight USAF E-3A Air Warning and Control System (AWACS) landing right; taxiing to stop; maintenance crew pushing with tow vehicle; placing chocks, crew deplaning; maintenance crew performing maintenance. Camels crossing in front of parked OH-58D, in desert. Various desert shots, showing marshal signaling as UH-60A lifts up, flies right, stirring up blowing sand. Various shots, Military Police (MP) inspecting Arab van before it enters Allied compound; includes opening and closing gate. Interior facility, female airmen talking about weather in Saudi. Various shots inside weather facility, showing airmen at computers; one is studying weather maps; another one looking at charts. Various shots, troops with gear and weapons offloading from CH-47C on desert; rotors are turning; troops marching away; several collapse from heat exhaustion and are treated by colleagues. Various shots unidentified captain talking into camera about munitions / weapons crew; pan to F-15C parked in below ground level ramp, pit; maintenance crew performing maintenance. Various shots, sidewinder missile on F-15C, then pan of area; sidewinder missiles on wheeled carriers. Interior facility, 20 mm munitions on conveyor belt and troops inspecting munitions. View of area, patriot missile launchers and F-15C parked in below ground level ramp, or pit. Various shots, maintenance crew performing Foreign Object Damage (FOD) walk. Various shots of Sheridan M5 type light tanks parked in sand; soldiers relaxing. Interior facility, troops using various types communications equipment. Airmen uploading Sidewinder missile on aircraft at night. Various shots, troops with gas masks at compound gate. Various shots, troops uploading bags, supposed to be mail, onto parked UH-60A. Various shots, decontamination team hosing down parked OH-58D. OH-58D lifting off right from ramp. CU, OH-58D landing on ramp, hosed down by decontamination team. Various desert shots, troops practicing ground warfare with M16s and M60s; crawling under, cutting barbed wire; running. CU - MS,, BAe Hunter taxiing left, then right, tail away on desert runway, country unknown. Master Sergeant Arthur De Roges from 438th Military Airlift Command (MAC), Airlift Control Squadron, Mission Support Team, talking about deployment, speech cut short. Various shots, black smoke in background; troops running; fire trucks spraying water; CU, interview with airman saying what he saw: thinks it was F-16 and he saw two parachutes eject. Also interview with Staff Sargent Paye from Hill Air Force Base, saying he saw two ejections but doesn`t know what aircraft it was. Various shots USAF KC-10 in flight, landing left; taxiing right; KC-10 and F-16C on ground in foreground; intercut with CU, F-16A from Hill AFB on ramp in foreground. Sequence, F-4Gs refueling from KC-135A, as seen from boom operator`s position. Sequence, British Sepecat Jaguar taxiing; taking off right, flying left, various angles; seen from chase aircraft, Royal Air Force (RAF) designation GRI. Interiors facility, Major Colonel, 4th TFW Hospital, Seymour-Johnson Air Force Base, explaining mass casualty exercises. Interior facility, Major Nigg, female, talking about gym facilities and recreation center. People working out in background. Includes close-up of people using exercise equipment; and riding stationary bikes. Interior facility, Secretary of Defense, Dick Cheney, talking to unidentified military personnel. Sign: WARNING RESTRICTED AREA. Note: This is facility Secretary Cheney is in, but it`s not identified. Sequence, facility door opens, Secretary Cheney and Very Important Persons (VIP) exit; walking to camouflage netting area; talking to press.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 1, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME209)
    Roll one (few shots end of roll).
    01-00-00-15
    Travelling shots of Kanan inside car towards Turkish border.
    External shots through car window at bleak flat landscape.
    01-03-03-21-4
    Kanan in car/shots through side window, overtaking lorry, back view of driver.
    Through windscreen.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 2, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME210)
    Zakho
    02:00-03-20 Night time shots of steam laundry.
    Exit shots of street - people walking, cars passing, exterior (ext.) of Baghdad hotel shop, shadowy figures outside shop - standing then walking past.
    02-02-55-12 Kanan walks along pavement, cars and lorry passing inside shop with shopkeeper and man looking at camera initially, pavement shots of people including children on pavement.
    Poster of Barzani on shop window.
    Kanan looks into shop window and walks past.
    Kanan into pool bar.
    02-05-49-21 Various shots of pool game.
    Kurdish TV and screen with stills of Kurdistan. Singer.
    Kanan watches tv in tea house.
    General views (gvs.) of Kanan in tea house. Kanan talks animatedly.
    Kanan talks to camera - soft shot - on first impressions.
    Sound and content not brilliant.
    02-12-00-14 Shots from car of headlamps.
    Travelling shots - lights in distance through windscreen of
    passing vehicles.
    Burning fire through windscreen.
    Out of car shots of fire and figures around it.
    Face of smiling boy in glow of fire. Gvs. of fire.
    Headlights of passing vehicle pan to fire.
    02-16-14-04 Ext. of houses and hotel with lit parts.
    02-17-59-00 Kanan walks around traffic island slogan which he reads out.
    "We want each Iraqi to have his conscience watch over him."
    Hotel wall slogan. "Discipline is necessary."
    02-21-05-04 Exterior of PRO office - people standing outside Kurdistan Relief Association sign.
    02-22-54-19 Travelling shots to first destroyed - Anfal - village across earth track. Landrover stops and then moves overhill. Shot of driver.
    Ext. shots of countryside.
    02-26-33-19--00 Kanan in back of landrover.
    02-29-21-02 Villager leads Kanan along track to destroyed village.
    "This was his house" - says Kanan - and is led to heap of rubble.
    Villager points and talks - Gvs. of overgrown terrain, Thistles.
    02-31-06-03 Man walks through to rubble and is followed by camera. He talks about his home, and then repeats what he has said. Shot of feet standing on rubble and then pan. Villager talks to Kanan atop rubble about anfal. (Translation needed of conversation.) Villager: "That's Mangesh over there.. ."
    Wide shot of area.
    02-35-42-08 Tracking behind villager through thistles. Concreted well and villager talks.
    Tracking behind villager walking towards destroyed school.
    Villager says he feel broken hearted: "I feel dead too."
    02-40-32-12 Shots through windscreen of landrover along main highway towards Sarseng.
    02-41-16-22 Sarseng Tractor drives past. Through windscreen shots along main road car ahead.
    02-42-31-07 Pesh Merga in car. Driver smoking cigarette.
    02-43-46-05 Amadya.
    Petrol station in Amadiya. Dumper truck arrives for petrol. Boy wheels away canister in wheelbarrow. Cars queue for petrol. Canisters stacked.
    02-47-53-10 Kanan (after encounter in Shaklawa): "Did you see that slimy soft-spoken polite little man? The one who came lurking up to me? 'Your venerable sir,' he said, 'who are you? Where do you come from?' 'Who did you think he was?' 'Obviously an agent, the cheapest kind.'"
    02-48-18-03 Broken tanks outside Shaklawa - tracking behind Kanan as he climbs up on tank. - "This is one of three tanks... when Masoud and 80 men... held back the Iraqi advance.
    Kanan looks into tank turret. "It's all burnt to hell. Never looked inside one of these things before."
    Shot tank, and Kanan talks: "This is a monument to one of the finer moments of the uprising."
    Wanders around tank with Kanan into shot much later.
    Wide shot of tank from across road.
    Destroyed armored personal carrier (APC).
    02-52-36-15 Kanan walks through Shaklawa with two pesh merga shots from behind and in front - walking and looking into shops.
    Kanan looks into shop/ shot of pesh merga. Photos of women on wall.
    "Famous Arab actresses up there." Walks on into Shkalawa filmed from behind. Kanan climbs into landrover with Pesh merga. Car starts and drives off.
    03-00-18-19 Landrover approaches slowly and pulls into side of road and stops - slow. Kanan gets out and walks towards camera.
    Another approach by landrover, stops and Kanan gets out, etc.
    Third attempt - best - vehicle pulls over and Kanan gets out with pm., walks down road followed by guards, driver gets in and starts car. Drives away - interior shot.
    Driver at pace.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 2A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME211)
    03-01-52-16 Repeat of getting into landrover.
    03-19-00 Kanan at bar on roof top in Saklawa. Street shots of man with mule. Children play boule(?). General views (gvs.) at bar table.
    03-05-20-00 First encounter with documents in Shaklawa. Kanan walks into building and then into room. "It's a mess." files, looks at 51 files and reads out from one. Thumbs through documents.
    Cutaways of men, one smoking. Man shows pictures of tortured man.
    "These pictures are of dead.. ." Kanan.
    Looks at pictures on table. Pictures taken of families. Kanan describes.
    "This gentleman first here when room was opened."
    Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) man talks; cutaway to bystander.
    Another room mentioned. Man shows us files. Looks at cassettes.
    03-15-40-17 Kanan leaves room and walks through corridors to new supply of documents. Iron doors clanged open, find film which studied in gloom.
    Kanan talks about letter on red cross. "Not to let members of relief agency members to travel around without permission from foreign ministry." (1991 Aug.)
    More film studied.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 3, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME212)
    Roll 3/3A
    03-00-06-13 Amadiya street shots, Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) headquarters general views (gvs.) of building, place where anfal victims were brought initially.
    Men standing on steps of building.
    03-01-16-02Is English transcription: man talking through landrover window to Kanan. Medium shot of him and Kanan. "What does word anfal mean to you?" Kanan, etc. "There is anfal in Koran."
    Shot of man from inside landrover. "You heard it on radio?"
    "Iraq Government... said we uproot revolution."
    Kamal talks about widows who lost families.
    03-07-45-23 and outside.
    Travel shots from Amadiya - Kanan in silhouette.
    Mountains and hills.
    03-09-59-15 PTC English transcription: Kanan: "I've come here to look for an archive.. ."
    03-12-23-14 GR: You've had your first contacts. What have you told them?"
    Kanan: "I'm feeling scared and excited at the same time dealing with very sensitive issue... dealing with something so explosive ..."
    GR: "Did they warn you about your own security?"
    Kanan: "Slipped piece of paper...only two or three people whom I can speak to."
    GR: "How did you put the issue to them?"
    Kanan: "Not about politics, about history... routinization of evil... way in which victims are really numbers... names on files... faceless."
    GR: "How important to find out details of anfal?"
    K: "Unimaginably important... transforms whole question. This kind of evil couldn't exist in 19th century. It's an issue that concerns everybody... It belongs to all of us because of the simple fact we're human beings."
    Exterior (ext.) of Saladhin hotel.
    03-18-25-04 Colonel Nab and the rest of MCC climb into helicopters and leave.
    Barzani's headquarters.
    03-23-07-08 English transcription: Kanan: on second meeting. Very good.
    Also chemical and biological weapons experiments. Problems of getting access.
    Sensitivity, tell us about informers, etc. Documents are politically dynamite, even part is better than nothing... opening up the body and going into the entrails tells you something new about the disease.
    Conditions on their use. It's about memory it is about overcoming what happened to Kurds themselves, whole society is complicit, this can only be exorcised by remembering... it's a matter of exorcism.
    28:47 How affect your plans for the Kurds? For the future?
    03-32-25-18 Dr. Mahmoud Osman meets Kanan.
    Dr. Mahmoud in English on meeting with Anfal, also on Sheikh Wassan and fate of survivors.
    Also talks about chemical weapons attacks north of Kirkuk and relates it to Anfal. Mentions Shoresh and Samut near Kalar. Anfal.
    43-59 Brought up in negotiations. Practically told people they had killed all people. Ali Hassan Majid directly questioned by Dr. Mahmoud, responsible for anfal. "He became angry... this point is finished... that means you want to irritate me, because I was responsible... we are now in a new, stage... this question couldn't be forgotten." Also on documents.
    37-17 English, refers to village.
    49-15 The documents.
    50-25 K's question.
    51-04 Osman's answer.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 3A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME213)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 4, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME214)
    04-01-39-03 General shots of Kanan entering Socialist Party headquarters and meeting Kanan.
    Lunch with Dr. Mahmoud on the meaning of anfal and why Ba'ath chose this word. "Chose it to show people they are attacking like those against Islam. Everything permitted. They wanted to show this religiously legal."
    04-06-16-01 Kanan inside Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) headquarters on why he's feeling so desperate.
    Meeting with PUK official who reschedules meeting.
    Kanan enters PUK headquarters in Shakqlawa and comes out.
    Jeep load of heavies with guns.
    General street shots outside main gate.
    Kanan in despair. "May if I don't get any documents, I should write, mail them for it, I'm upset we've been given the run-around. Typical middle eastern style of politics.. ." Two takes. Second take best.
    PUK officials says we will only have half an hour.
    04-16-120-23 Street scenes of Shaklawa. N.B. white balance initially.
    Meetings with Iraqi Shiites who sought refuge in Shaklawa, waiting for families.
    Kanan talks to them: "They've all come from the south of Iraq."
    Street shots of Shiites.
    04-22-07-20 Inside landrover - Kanan, one man came skulking up.
    Travel shots from inside landrover. Second mention on man whom he thought was agent.
    04-23-58-01 Jelal Talabani. Experiments on humans with chemical and biological weapons. Jelal: "I'm sure they used them." "We have some problems with sources... the man will be hanged..." "some in very important posts ..." Talks about the fate of the missing. 30,0000 to 40,000 are them are children.
    04-28-03-16 Two shots of Talabani and Kanan on proposals to use documents for study in centre. PUK ready for full cooperation. Go to Mr. Barzani. He doesn't want to disturb relations with Baghdad. We don't want to have war in winter time.
    Shows Talabani letters from Harvard. "We have a film. They are taking a lady.
    (Handwritten on shot lists.)
    Being snubbed by PUK, bigger issues than party politics.
    11-27 Talabani says lots of documents in hands of "people." PUK W~ba 3 has "rooms and rooms." "Of course, you can see everything." "Can we film them in the location?" "Yes."
    Talabani promises all assistance.
    He talks of the rape story, he talks of rape story but doesn't finish.
    04-00-03-13 Kanan writing diary/notes in his room in Zakho. Kanan interviews Supki in PRP. (He does not want his face shown.)
    04-02-35-03 First contact with Anfal story.
    Talks about 13 people killed in front of family in village near Zakho.
    "Nobody cares. No humanitarian organisation, no NGOs, even parties. No one gives any assistance to these people. They have been swallowed in the towns."
    Kanan - asks about Abrush family whom we later meet. General background. One family suffered from chemical weapons attacks - families taken to prison and then, disappear.
    Kanan: "What does Anfal mean?"
    Off camera: "It's a holy war against the infidel, free to take women and girls."
    K: "Trying to understand significance. Anfal is when they took everyone."
    "It's a genocide against the Kurds."
    Follows explanation of Ba'ath vision of anfal - "They were taking to take fish from the water."
    Explanation of security zones being set up after 1975.
    Reads lists.
    0-4-17-56-04 Shots of lists prepared by Supki.
    Mention of Abrush family, and circumstances surrounding the 3~1 disappearance of family members. Mention of children dying in Baharka. Capture of family in 1988 Aug. Taken to Dohuk castle. Some taken to Baharka. Village demolished. Supki flicks through lists. Close up of lists.
    04-26-05-12 Supki: "Those people are in need of help."
    Holds up picture of one lady who has lost two children.
    Husband was kidnapped in 1988. One child died in prison and the other in Baharka.
    "In Zakho alone some 5000 people have been disappeared."
    Holds up more pictures.
    04-29-41-14 Abrush family: Zakho/interior. Three shots. Shirko tells how people disappeared at checkpoints outside, Mosul translating for brother. Brother tells story. Mother tells story. Picture of missing brother/father. Shot of survivors who ended up in Baharka. Exterior shots of family.
    04-49-46-04 General views (gvs.) of Zakho. (Wind noise.) Zoom in and out.
    Wedding bus passes with music and little boy being dragged along by it.
    More gvs. mountains outside Zahko. Pull back.
    04-52-43-09 Army fort with man praying in front of it. Two guards sitting outside fort. (Wind noise.)
    Kanan goes up and meets them. They go inside fort.
    Kanan is shown around. Guards are ex-soldiers but Arab.
    Group goes up stairs.
    "They are deserters. They are defending this police station." (Protecting water plant.)
    K. talks to two Arab soldiers. One from Baghdad.
    04-57-32-07 Kanan ptc at destroyed village. Holds up piece of cloth.
    "One way of looking at horror, something truly horrible happened here.
    00-39 Retake which good: "Two kinds of horror here... piece of cloth... how many such villages... what mind behind it... anfal.
    Scale: "No-one knows... trying to count names... the secret is knowable it was systematic plan."
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 4A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME215)
    05-03-14-19 Dohuk Fort - where villagers were brought. People entering - long shot and pull out. Travelling shot into fort behind landrover. (Wind screen dirty.) Through main portals into sun. Shots of interior of fort. Kanan walks around. Burnt out walls, overturned vehicles. Children on balcony. Families. Woman with water container on shoulder walks into fort. Inside kitchen, Kanan ptc. "No good comes to a nation that eats more than it produces." "Slogans like this get to the mind of the regime almost as good as the papers we are looking for."
    Retake which good.
    Two boys look at camera. Woman washes dishes on floor.
    General views (gvs.) of Dohuk from roadside.
    05-15-43-22 Wedding sequence en route to Saladhin. Kanan looks on. Bride waits in car. Travelling shots behind wedding cars.
    05-21-20-11 Saddam's palace from afar. The wall surrounding the enclave. Pesh merga walks by. Soldier section. Various shots. Kanan's encounter with Iraqi soldiers. Lorry drives and barbed wire replaced. Iraqi soldier walks back. Pesh merga and soldiers confront each other. Kanan asks what secrets they are concealing.
    05-27-38-18 Gvs. of Amadiya. Beautiful.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 5, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME216)
    05-06-50-03 Talabani – on sex video shot by Muhbarat, etc., Sheikh Wassan story.
    9:45 Talabani and Kanan exterior shots.
    05-10-13-17 Asshad - "Kurdistan is not computerised." Pleading between him and Kanan in landrover.
    11:40 Kanan - "He wanted to bring us here at night. It's not going to be an easy matter. I just want a sense of scale."
    Inside landrover again. Drive to the building where documents kept. "Don't bring the camera."
    Kanan and Ashad talk in Arabic.
    Interior: Asshad. "I'm going to Arbil with the UN."
    K: "I want to come tonight."
    A:"I have to go."
    Meeting with keeper of the documents - in Arabic.
    24-38 Kanan explains above.
    27-10 Art exhibition - various grim pictures, raven picking out eyes of young girl, crucifixion scenes.
    35-01 Travelling shot with landrover. Exterior (ext.)
    (Near Shaklawa.)
    36-15 Street scenes in Shaklawa. Landrover passes.
    37-18 Dusk shots of herd of sheep in Shaklawa from balcony.
    (Same place as before - roll 2.)
    37-45 Kanan inside room with documents - first encounter.
    Kanan describes their provenance.
    "This is the section dealing with the investigation of people's thoughts?"
    What do you mean with people's thoughts?"
    Responses.
    Flicking through file, Kanan studies documents. Excerpts from documents.
    41-31 "Densest collection of files concern those that probe into people's thoughts.. .," K
    42-00 Security maps.
    43-54 Hunting through files on floor. Excerpts.
    Primitive filing system. "Routing business of recording... mixture of fact and fiction... is this world is or imagined to be... one great big jumble," etc.